这是1965 年十一月发生的真实故事
These are the true events of November, 1965
越南的德浪山谷
The la Drang Valley of Vietnam
一个我们国家遗忘的地方
a place our country does not remember...
一场它所不了解的战争
in a war it does not understand.
这个故事是那些年轻美国人的一份遗嘱
This story's a testament to the young Americans...
他们死在死亡山谷中
who died in the Valley of Death...
也是对越南军队中那些年轻人的纪念
and a tribute to the young men of the Peoples Army of Vietnam...
他们在那个地方死在我们手里
who died by our hand in that place.
这个故事,要从最初说起
To tell this story, I must start at the beginning.
但是它从哪里开始呢
But where does it begin?
也许是在1954年六月 当法国第100集团军
Maybe in June of 1954, when French Group Mobile 100...
搬进这个越南中央高地
moved into the same Central Highlands of Vietnam...
我们 11 年后要去的地方
where we would go 11 years later.
看到什么？
没有队长
该死的草丛
热得要命
该死的国家
[法语]
[越南语]
抓俘虏吗？
不全杀掉
他们就不会再入侵的
【我 们 曾 是 战 士】
也许故事该从美国说起
Maybe the story begins in America...
当军方开始意识到一种新的战争即将来临
when the army first realized a new kind of war was coming its way.
白宫希望开始战争而且
The White House anticipates a buildup and wants a victory...
取得一场胜利 对那些穿土布衣服的野蛮人
over cavemen in black pajamas.
如果不是他们打败了法国人 我们不会去那儿
We wouldn't be there if they hadn't already beaten the French Army.
法国的军队 那是什么
The French Army? What's that?
问题出在越南的地形，丛林 高山 大河
The problem in Vietnam is terrain jungles, mountains, rivers.
军队的梦魇
Maneuver's a nightmare.
我们有一个计划 使用直升飞机--在战斗中来去自如
We have a plan to use helicopters leap in and out of battle.
他们想要你来试验一下这个想法
They want you to run the test on the idea.
这需要一个厉害的指挥官
It'll take a hell of a combat leader.
我认识一个年轻上校Hal Moore
I know a young light colonel named Hal Moore.
他在朝鲜指挥过一次战役
He led a combat company in Korea.
在那之后，他自愿去测试实验降落伞
After that, he volunteered to test experimental parachutes.
实验降落伞? 听起来挺合适
Experimental parachutes? Sounds like just the guy.
The other side of the mountain was all that he could see
Was all that he could see Was all that he could see
The bear went over the mountain The bear went over the mountain
The bear went over the mountain
我们接着 "Bingo"何如 你们说什么? "Bingo"
How about we go back to "Bingo"? What do you say? "Bingo".
B-I-N-G-O
Bingo是他的名字
And Bingo was his name-o
汤姆,关于我们新上校,你知道多少
Tom, how much you know about our new colonel?
他是在朝鲜
He was in Korea...
哈佛国际关系硕士学位
has a master's in international relations from Harvard.
哈佛? 他不是学院里的那些猫之一,是吗
Harvard? He's not one of those academic pussies, is he?
Hal Moore?
想要我拿一个
Want me to get one of those?
加油,太高了 吉米你最好的发球
Come on, Too Tall. Gimme your best shot!
你看见那吗,运动迷 你看见那吗
Did you see that, sports fans? Did you see that?
Snakeshit drives that one to the moon, baby!
撞他
Hit the cutoff man! Hit the cutoff man!
来了
And he's coming around!
他来这里了 不是吧
- Here he comes! - No, he's not.
出局了
You're out! You're out!
难怪你不能飞 你看不到
Horseshit! No wonder you can't fly. You can't see.
我相信你挂了
I believe you're out.
- 你是飞行员? - 我太高了,sir
- You're a pilot? - Too Tall, sir.
- 是的,看得出 - 你呼叫,我们运送
- Yeah, I can see that. - You call, we haul.
- 能跟你谈谈吗,Crandall - 好的,sir
- Can I speak to you, Crandall? - Yes, sir.
- 出局 - 对了
- Out. - Safe.
- 请你喝一杯？ - 当然可以
- Can I buy you a drink? - Sure.
谢谢
Thanks.
你的人叫你 "Snakeshit"
So, your men call you "Snakeshit".
那是弟兄们起的,sir
That's an affectionate appellation of my comrades-in-arms, sir...
因为我飞得比Snakeshit低
'cause I fly lower than snake shit.
我有个问题,Snakeshit,你来解决
Well, I got a problem, Snakeshit, and I think you're the solution.
我被叫做好多东西,上校,却从不是个解决
I've been called a lot of things, Colonel, never a solution.
你知道什么是空中骑兵
You know what air cavalry really means?
你飞入敌占区,离家10,000多里
You fly into hostile territory, outnumbered 10,000 miles from home.
有时战场比足球场还小
Sometimes the battleground's no bigger than a football field.
如果直升机不来,我们会被杀光
And if the choppers stop comin', we all get slaughtered.
我打赌飞行员不会因为陌生人飞过来
Now, I figure chopper pilots won't fly into hell for strangers...
我是Hal Moore
so... I'm Hal Moore.
我知道,sir 为什么是我们
I know, sir. Why us?
你们看起来像粪一样 但是你们的装备还好
Well, you guys look like shit, but your equipment is immaculate.
昨天是星期天，你不必训练，但你参加了
Yesterday was Sunday. You didn't have to be training, but you were.
你是飞行员了 像那个太高
You got pilots like that Too Tall character.
他超过了普通军队的标准
He's way outside the limits of army regs.
为什么他们愿意和你一起飞
They wanna fly with you for some reason.
我猜因为他们认为你是最好的
I guess it's 'cause they think you're the best.
因为我只是个新兵哑一些,sir
It's 'cause I only recruit the dumb ones, sir.
不 在所有这些中我有个选择
I don't suppose I have a choice in all this.
你当然不
You sure don't.
为了世界不要错过
Wouldn't miss it for the world.
为空中骑兵
To the Air Cav.
早上好,长官
Good mornin', Sergeant Major.
你知道今天是什么鬼日子？
How do you know what kind of goddamn day it is?
集合！立正！
Group! Atten-hut!
稍息,先生们
At ease, gentlemen.
欢迎加入新的骑兵队伍
Welcome to the new cavalry.
我们将会投入到战争
We will ride into battle.
这个... 将会是我们的坐骑
And this... will be our horse.
你不须捕捉它，喂它
You don't have to catch it. You don't have to feed it.
但是我要提醒你们
But I can assure you...
新的技术或者你的军衔
that neither the new technology nor your status as officers...
都不会让你免除危险
will keep you above the danger.
Plumley长官和我来自伞兵
Sergeant-Major Plumley and I come from the paratroopers...
那里官员总是第一个跳出飞机
where the officer is always the first one out of the plane.
为了跟随你的本能
Because to follow your instincts...
激发你手下的斗志
and to inspire your men by your example...
和他们一起作战
you have to be with them where the metal meets the meat.
二战中Plumley长官指挥4个跳伞队
Sergeant-Major Plumley made all four combat jumps...
在第82空降师
in the 82nd Airborne during World War II.
西西里，沙伦劳，诺曼第
Sicily, Salerno, Normandy...
和荷兰，还有朝鲜
and Holland, plus one more in Korea.
他由我指挥
He answers to me and to me alone.
现在，我希望你们喜欢训练
Now, I hope you gentlemen like training...
因为我和长官
'cause me and the sergeant-major
我们爱它
we love it.
三次不到你不会被开除
Three strikes and you're not out!
总有一件让你能做更多的事
There is always one more thing you can do.
出发,男孩
Here we go, boys.
过去! 现在
Move! Move! Go! Now!
二 走
- Two. - Let's go!
三
Three.
我们在外面这里
We're outta here!
很好,哼!? 很好
- Pretty good, huh? - Pretty good.
只有一件事是错的
There's only one thing wrong.
快，我们会是营里最好的排了
Be sharp! We will be the best platoon in this battalion!
准备 出发
Be ready in there! Let's go! Let's go!
好了 首长死了
All right! Your officer's dead!
你该做什么?  第一
- What do you do? What do you do? - First
他犹豫 他死了，你做什么?
All right, he hesitated. He's dead. What do you do?
跳下飞机 下来
- Get off the chopper! - Get off the chopper.
抓住第三个
Hold off the third one.
继续
Come on in.
Savage,你向上级学习怎么做
Savage, you learn the job of the man above you...
再教你的手下
and you teach your job to the man below you in rank.
每个人都这样做
That goes for every man in this outfit.
明白? 是的,sir
- Understood? - Yes, sir!
我们将会在战场上着陆
We'll be landing under fire, gentlemen.
会没命的
Men will die.
你们有祷告过吗?
Have you said your prayers?
快点 我和你一起来
Come on. I'll say them with you.
下来 吉米，那只熊
- Fall in. - Gimme that bear.
好了吗 预备，开始
All right. Ready. Set.
In the name of the Father, the Son and the Holy Ghost.
Hail Mary, full of grace, the Lord is with thee.
Blessed art thou amongst women...
and blessed is the fruit of thy womb Jesus.
Holy Mary, Mother of God, pray for us sinners
Cecile,我听不到你祈祷,宝贝
Cecile, I don't hear you praying, honey.
我不想做天主教徒的 我想和妈咪一样，做Nethodist
I don't wanna be Catholic. I wanna be a "Nethodist" like Mommy.
你?
You do?
为什么呢?
And why is that, honey?
无论我想要什么我都能祈祷
So I can pray whatever I want.
那是罪
That's a sin.
不,那不是罪
No, that's not a sin.
上帝仅仅使你冷静，它不是罪
God just made you hardheaded. It's not a sin.
我来告诉你，你想
I'll tell you what. You wanna
你不为我们的家祈祷而且谢谢上帝?
You wanna pray and thank God for our family?
- 想,sir - 那很好，我们开始
- Yes, sir. - That's good. Let's do it.
Hail Mary, full of grace, the Lord is with thee.
Blessed art thou among women...
and blessed is the fruit of thy womb, Jesus.
我能听到你笑 你知道,甚至在这里
I can hear you laughing, you know, even in here.
我不是笑,我是吃惊
I'm not laughing, I'm marveling.
吃惊?怎么了
Marveling? At what?
你能在你的孩子中找到顽固
That you can find stubbornness in your children...
我想它来自任何人，除了你
and think it comes from anybody but you.
是吗 嗯
- Yeah? - Mm-hmm.
我将给你一件事让你吃惊
I'll give you something to marvel at.
他是一个野性的男人
He's a wild man.
- 当我祈祷的时候 - 嗯
- When I pray - Mm-hmm.
无论我想要什麽
whatever I want
感谢上帝把你给了我
I thank God for you.
美丽的早晨,长官
Beautiful morning, Sergeant Major.
你是作什麽的,该死的气象预报员现在?
What are you, a fuckin' weatherman now?
看我为棒球运动员所找到的
Look what I found for the new baseball player.
- 送给我们另一串官员 - 哼
- Sent us another bunch of officers. - Uh-huh.
真正的绿色 必须训练了
Real green. Gotta train 'em up.
让我以为在新的部门
Makes me think I'm starting a new unit.
他们也送了新的来福枪，M-16
They sent new rifles too. The M-16.
那是相当好的武器
That's supposed to be a pretty good weapon.
许多塑料
Lots of plastic.
对我感觉像一只 BB 枪 相信我将只用手枪
Feels like a BB gun to me. Believe I'll stick with my pistol.
你认为我们会离敌人那么近?
You think we're gonna get close enough to the enemy to use that?
你想什么,sir?
What do you think, sir?
领袖要保持冷静
A leader must remain cool and calm.
并且他一定要学会不理睬爆炸
And second, he must learn to ignore explosions...
热浪和灰尘,受伤者的尖叫声
the heat and dust, the screams of the wounded.
这是战场上的常事 常事
This is normal on a battlefield. Normal!
Fortran,你需要拿队伍加强左边侧面
Fortran, you need to get a company over to reinforce the left flank.
- 那是来自哪里? - 那在越南，我们的顾问
- Where is that coming from? - That's our advisors in Vietnam.
新收音机收到的
The new radio's picking up atmospheric bounce.
当狂马是个婴孩的时候
When Crazy Horse was a baby...
他接受部落中每个女人哺乳
he nursed from the breast of every woman in the tribe.
苏人那样养他们的孩子
The Sioux raised their children that way.
战士们
Every warrior...
叫部落中每个女人"母亲"
called every woman in the tribe "mother".
每个比较年长的战士 他们称他为 "祖父"
Every older warrior, they called him "grandfather".
所以他们打仗如同一个家庭
Now, the point here is that they fought as a family.
照顾你的人
Take care of your men.
教他们彼此照顾
Teach them to take care of each other.
因为当这个开始
'Cause when this starts...
每个人是我们拥有的
each other is all we're gonna have.
- 你调的那吗? - 是的,sir
- Did you tune that in? - Yes, sir.
不错 你做我的无线电技师
Well, that's fine. You're my radio operator.
你将会很好 你将会胜任的
You'll be fine. You'll work it out.
你们中的任何一个叫我爷爷
Any of you sons of bitches calls me Grandpa...
我会杀了他
I'll kill ya.
Godboldt,脱掉你的长靴
Godboldt, take your boots off.
继续
Go on.
每个人,脱掉你的长靴 每个人
Everybody, take your boots off. Everybody.
袜子
Socks too.
穿上新袜子
I want you to draw fresh socks from supply.
涂上药粉
Keep your feet dusted with powder.
每个人互相检查脚就像Godboldt和我一样
Everybody check each other's feet like Godboldt and me.
现在,那个年轻人像个领袖
Now, that young man's a leader.
是的,sir
Yes, sir.
其他人 那个大的,结实的
That other fella that big, strong one there
他想要赢得奖章
he wants to win medals.
为什么你落在后面?
Why were you in the back?
见鬼,为什么你最后?
Goddamn it, why were you in the back?
他很热心
He's eager.
女士们, 我很高兴你们今天在这里
Ladies, I'm really, really glad you're here today.
你们其中有些是新人，我们都是新到岗位
Some of you are new to the army and all of us are new to this post.
我们要利用我们的资源，解决我们的问题
I thought we'd pool our resources and cover questions we have.
我们从第一项开始-- 食物
So, why don't we start with item number one food.
哪里买东西最好?
Where's the best place to shop?
我试过Big star,它不错
Well, I tried Big Star, and it's okay.
但我经常买些没用的东西
But I keep thinking my water's gonna break right in the checkout aisle.
刚才是食品，现在第二项-- 洗衣
That takes care of food shopping. So, item number two laundry.
洗衣机不动了
The base washing machines don't work.
他们从沼泽执行完任务身上都是沙子
They're full of sand from the swamp missions.
我会注意那个
I'll take care of that.
- 我已经抱怨过了 - 我们将会去告诉将军
- I've already complained. - We'll just go to the general.
同时，镇上Laundromat挺好
In the meantime, the Laundromat in town's okay...
但是他们不让在机器上洗彩色的衣物
but they won't let you wash your colored things in their machines.
- 在公众的Laundromat? - 对我而言也不可能
- At a public Laundromat? - Didn't make sense to me either.
我告诉你,他们在窗户上有标示
I'm telling you, they have a sign right in the window...
说 "只能白色"
says "Whites Only".
- 什么? - 他们意谓只能白人
- What? - They mean white people only.
太可怕了
That's awful.
你的丈夫穿着军装
Your husband is wearing the uniform of a country that allows a place...
这里的洗衣店却说他不能用,当他可以为之而死--
to say his laundry's not good enough, when he could die for
- 对不起，我只是-- - 没关系，亲爱的
- I'm sorry. I just - That's all right, honey.
我知道我丈夫为何而战，我很骄傲
I know what my husband's fighting for, and that's why I can smile.
我丈夫从不要求得到尊重
My husband will never ask for respect...
他只会尊重像他一样的人
and he'll give respect to no man who hasn't earned it.
他家庭其馀人也是这样的态度
The rest of his family is the same way.
不尊重他的人可以抱着洗衣机
Anybody who doesn't respect that can keep his washing machine...
我孩子的衣服可以用其他方法洗
'cause my baby's clothes are gonna be clean anyway.
好吧, 第二项就这些了
Well, I guess that takes care of item number two.
你还好吧?
Are you all right?
我想-- 我想 我的水要断掉了
I think I think my water just broke.
稳住 稳住
We're all calm. We're all calm.
叫车
A car! A car!
- 上校 - 稍息，稍息
- Colonel. - At ease. At ease.
我听说中尉做爸爸了
I heard one of my new lieutenants just became a father.
- 我来祝贺 - 谢谢你,sir
- I came to say congratulations. - Thank you, sir.
我没有打扰你
So, I didn't wanna disturb you.
不，这样好 没关系
No, it's fine. It's all right. Please.
你太太怎么样?
Well, how's your wife?
她很好，正在睡觉
She's okay. She's okay. She's sleeping.
我女儿也是，我只是
So is my daughter. I just...
想在这里待一会儿，见她之前
wanted to be here for a while before I held her.
已经见过她了?
Well, tag her already?
- 那是什么? - Camille。对不起,sir
- What's that say? - Camille. Sorry about this, sir.
别脱下，带着吧，这是命令
Don't take that off. Leave that where it is. That's an order.
- 上校,我可以问你一个问题吗? - 当然
- Colonel, may I ask you a question? - Sure.
你怎么看一个士兵同时也是父亲呢?
What do you think about being a soldier and a father?
我觉得互相补充
I hope that being good at the one...
相得益彰
makes me better at the other.
为什么? 你认为呢?
Why? What about you?
我不知道,sir
I don't know, sir.
在学院和这里
Between college and here...
芭芭拉和我在非洲过了一年
Barbara and I spent a year in Africa.
我们帮助建立了一所孤儿学校
We helped build a school for orphans.
他们成了孤儿是因为另一边的军阀
They were orphans because the warlord across the border...
不喜欢他们的种族
didn't like their tribe.
我知道上帝有一个计划
I know God has a plan for me.
我仅仅希望它可以帮助保护孤儿
I just hope it's to help protect orphans...
而不是制造孤儿
not make any.
好吧，为什么我们不求求他?
Well, why don't we ask him?
来，祈祷吧
Come on. Let's go ask him.
天堂里我们的父亲, 在我们参加战争之前
Our Father in Heaven, before we go into battle...
庇佑我们每个战士
every soldier among us will approach you each in his own way.
也庇佑我们的敌人
Our enemies too...
依照他们自己的理解
according to their own understanding...
请求保护和胜利
will ask for protection and for victory.
因此，我们跪在你无限的智慧面前
And so, we bow before your infinite wisdom.
虔诚地祈祷
We offer our prayers as best we can.
我祈祷你照看年轻人,如同Jack Geoghegan
I pray you watch over the young men, like Jack Geoghegan...
我带他们上战场
that I lead into battle.
你赐我力量在可怕的战争里
You use me as your instrument in this awful hell of war...
看护他们
to watch over them.
尤其是像我身边这样的人
Especially if they're men like this one beside me...
在你的祝福和赞词中拥有未来
deserving of a future in your blessing and good will.
- 阿门 - 阿门
- Amen. - Amen.
对了,还有 主啊
Yes, and one more thing, dear Lord...
关于我们的敌人--
about our enemies
不要理睬他们的异教祈祷
ignore their heathen prayers...
帮忙我们把那些小杂种打下地狱
and help us blow those little bastards straight to hell.
阿门，再一次
Amen again.
阿门
Amen.
谢谢你
Thank you.
你要听关于苹果树 , 会飞的马
There's one about the kid with the apple tree, or the flying horse...
还是有鹿和其他东西的故事呢
or the fairy tales with the deer and stuff in 'em.
爸爸,战争是什么?
Daddy, what is a war?
战争是
A war is a
它是
Well, it's
它是不该发生却发生了
It's something that shouldn't happen, but it does.
当有些人
It's when...
在另外的国家或任何国家中
some people in another country or any country
想剥夺其他人的生命
try to take the lives of other people.
像你爸爸这样的军人必须
And then soldiers like your daddy have to
去那里阻止他们，这是我的工作
It's my job to go over there and stop them.
他们想要取走你的生命,爸爸?
Are they gonna try to take your life away, Daddy?
是的，他们要试一试
Well, yes, they're gonna try.
我不让
But I'm not gonna let 'em.
好
Okay?
睡不着?
Can't sleep?
他们这么年轻
The men are so young and
有些是新婚夫妇
Now they sent me a new crop even greener.
看着他们
When I look at them, I...
就像我们的孩子
see our boys.
那你正是要带领他们的男人
Well, then you're just the man to lead them.
我试着
I guess.
我们想要说服共产主义者
We intend to convince the Communists...
我们不能够被军队的力量击败
that we cannot be defeated by force of arms.
我问过指挥官Westmoreland将军
I have asked the commanding general, General Westmoreland...
他需要什么来击败那些游击队
what more he needs to meet this mounting aggression.
他告诉我
He has told me...
我们将会满足他的需要
and we will meet his needs.
今天我命令空军到越南
I have today ordered to Vietnam the airmobile division...
还有一些其他部队去加强战斗力
and certain other forces which will raise our fighting strength...
从 75,000 到
from 75,000 to...
125,000个人立即出发。
125,000 men almost immediately.
迟一些还有更多的部队投入
Additional forces will be needed later.
找出你们最好的衣服,女士们
Get out your best dresses, ladies.
他们将要庆祝了
They're gonna want to celebrate.
Don't you ever be sad
Lean on me when the times are bad
我没听总统说过紧急状况
I didn't hear the president mention a state of emergency.
他没说过
No, he didn't.
没有告示征募将不会是扩大的
Well, without that declaration our enlistments won't be extended.
对不起,Hal
I'm sorry, Hal.
原谅我,sir,直接告诉我吧
Forgive me, sir, but let me get this straight.
我们用这种从未在战场上试用过的技术
We form a division using techniques never attempted in battle...
来对抗在他土地上有20年作战经验的敌人
against an enemy with 20 years of combat experience on his ground...
离我们国家12,000 里远
12,000 miles away from our ground.
而且把我们送上战场之前
And right before the army sends us into the fight...
他们调走我三分之一富有经验的人,包括指挥官
they take away a third of my most experienced men, including officers.
我也不不愿意这样，Hal
I don't like it any better than you do, Hal.
你看见了,不是吗
You saw this coming, didn't you?
是的。那是你为什么给了我那些新人
Yes. That's why you gave me that new crop of platoon leaders.
朝鲜没有教会他们任何东西
Korea didn't teach 'em anything.
- 政客? - 政客
- Politicians? - Politicians.
Hold me, hold me
Never let me go
Until you've told me told me
What I want to know and then just hold me
Hold me Make me tell you
I'm in love with you
Thrill me, thrill me
谢谢,sir
Thank you, sir.
顺便一提,Hal，我们被调离后
By the way, Hal, since we're being deployed...
他们重编了队伍
they're renumbering the units.
你现在是指挥官
You're now the commanding officer...
第7骑兵师第1营
of the 1st Battalion of the 7th Cavalry.
第7师
The 7th.
如同Custer一般的团
The same regiment as Custer.
谢谢你,sir
Thank you, sir.
Be sensible with your new love
Don't be fooled thinking
This is the last you'll find
But they never stood in the dark
With you, love
When you take me in your arms
And drive me slowly out of my mind
Kiss me, kiss me
And when you do I'll know
看看你们周围
Look around you.
在第7骑兵师
In the 7th Cavalry...
有一位从乌克兰来的上尉
we got a captain from the Ukraine.
另一个来自波多黎各
Another from Puerto Rico.
有日本人,中国人
We've got Japanese, Chinese...
黑人，西语裔 Cherokee印第安人
Blacks, Hispanics, Cherokee Indians.
犹太人和非犹太人
Jews and gentiles.
都是美国人
All Americans.
现在,在这个国家
Now, here in the States...
这个部队中的一些人
some men in this unit...
可能经历着种族或是宗教歧视
may experience discrimination because of race or creed.
但是现在对你们和我来说
But for you and me now...
这些都不存在了
all that is gone.
我们将进驻死亡阴影山谷
We're moving into the Valley of the Shadow of Death...
你要看护身边的人
where you will watch the back of the man next to you...
而他也会看护着你
as he will watch yours.
你将不关心他是什么肤色
And you won't care what color he is...
或者他把上帝叫做什么
or by what name he calls God.
我们将要离开家
They say we're leaving home.
我们将要去那个被成为家的地方
We're going to what home was always supposed to be.
因此让我们了解情形
So let us understand the situation.
我们将要上战场
We are going into battle...
与冷酷的敌人作战
against a tough and determined enemy.
我不能答应你们
I can't promise you...
会带着所有人活着回来
that I will bring you all home alive.
但是在这里我发誓
But this I swear
在你们和全能的主面前
before you and before Almighty God
当我们上战场时
that when we go into battle...
我将会第一个踏上战场
I will be the first to set foot on the field...
最后一个离开
and I will be the last to step off.
我不会丢下任何人
And I will leave no one behind.
无论死去的或是活着的
Dead or alive...
我们所有人会一起回家
we will all come home together.
帮助我，上帝
So help me God.
我爱你
I love you.
Hal,昨晚敌人在 Plaei Me碰上了我们的营地
Hal, last night the enemy hit our camp at Plaei Me.
- 多少伤亡? - 没有
- How many casualties? - None.
敌人撤回到这座山
The enemy forces withdrew toward this mountain...
靠近高棉的边界
near the Cambodian border.
你有多少人准备好了开战
How many men do you have battle-ready?
- 长官 - 395,sir
- Sergeant Major? - Three hundred ninety-five, sir.
好
Exactly.
你如何估计敌人的力量
What do you estimate the enemy strength?
我们难以估计,上校
We appraise their numbers as manageable, Colonel.
你不知道
You have no idea.
我们不知道，简单的命令,Hal
We have no idea. Simple orders, Hal.
找到敌人，杀掉他
Find the enemy and kill him.
他们攻击我们, 没有伤亡 他们在山中奔跑躲藏
They attack us, no casualties. They run and hide in the mountains.
自然该我们找他们, 当然
Naturally we chase them, of course.
看来你喜欢埋伏
Smell like an ambush to you?
他们近到可以杀我们 我们也会近得可以杀他们
They get close enough to kill us, we'll be close enough to kill them.
乘直升机来回,30 分钟
Round trip by chopper, 30 minutes.
如此最初地上的60个人将会在那里单独待上半个小时
So the first 60 men on the ground will be there half an hour alone.
婊子
Son of a bitch.
你应该拿你自己的M-16
I think maybe you ought to get yourself that M-16.
时间到了，我要一把，地上还有很多
Time comes I need one, there'll be plenty of 'em lying on the ground.
好吧，去做我们来这里要做的
Well, let's go do what we came here to do.
是,sir
Yes, sir.
Garry Owen!
今天是星期天
It was a Sunday.
1965年十一月14日
November 14, 1965.
在那天之前,越南北部的军人
Before that day, the soldiers of North Vietnam...
和美国军人
and those of America...
从未在主战场上遭遇过
never met each other in a major battle.
在两里外，贴地飞行
Two miles out. Dropping to nap of the earth.
第一排,行动
First Platoon, let's move!
这是Troyjan2，所有人维持连络，结束
This is Trojan Two. All units maintain perimeter contact. Over.
侦察兵 抓住他
It's a scout! Let's take him prisoner!
嗨，中尉
Hey! Lieutenant!
他去在那里了，快点
There he goes! Come on!
快
Come on!
上尉, 你与所有人保持联络
Captain, I want you to keep in contact with all patrols.
嗨,我抓到什么了 一个男孩! 这里
Hey, I got something here. I got a boy! Here.
男孩,该死
Boy, hell.
那不是男孩
That ain't no boy.
- 他说他一个背弃者。 - 胡说,他是哨兵
- He say he a deserter. - Bullshit, he's a lookout.
问他他的朋友在哪里
Ask him where his friends are.
他说这是整个队伍的基地
He say this is base camp of whole division.
- 4,000人 - 哪里
- Four thousand men. - Where?
那座山
That mountain.
这支军队干掉了法国人
Same army destroyed French.
而且他说他们要杀美国人 非常想
And he say they want kill American very badly.
只是找不到
Just not been able to find any yet.
Metsker上尉,告诉所有的巡逻 守住位置
Captain Metsker, tell all patrols to hold their positions.
你,带上无线电
You, take the radio!
- 他们在哪里 - sir,我们必须抓住那家伙
- Where are they? - Sir, we gotta get that guy!
召集所有巡逻
Call in all the patrols!
我们要交火了 大家小心
We have to engage the enemy as far away from the LZ as possible!
呼叫,呼叫 这是Troyjan2
Net Call, Net Call, this is Trojan-Two.
抓住受伤者 连络中断
Grab the wounded! Break contact!
后撤 占据制高点
Fall back! Get to high ground!
火力掩护 到达制高点
Cover fire! Get to high ground!
快
Come on!
快!上来 带伤员到中间来
Come on! Get up here! Bring the wounded up to the middle!
走
Move it, move it!
掩护
Cover fire! Cover fire!
都趴下
Everybody down! Down!
检查弹药 每个人检查弹药
Check your ammo! Everybody check ammo!
快点 我们要离开这里
Come on! I'll get us out of here!
抓住受伤者 我们要走了
Grab the wounded! We'll make a run
- Sarge - 我们必须离开这里
- Sarge! - We gotta get out of here!
蹲下，任何人不要动
Stay down! Don't anybody move!
Bungum，蹲下
Bungum, stay down!
你会好的
You're gonna be okay.
蹲下
Stay down.
掩护
Form a perimeter!
保存弹药，趴下
Conserve your ammo and stay down!
巡逻的怎么了
What's happening with those patrols?
我正在联络他们,sir 这是Troyjan2，呼叫，完毕
I'm trying to reach them, sir! This is Trojan-Two! Come in! Over!
嗨，稳住
Hey! Hey! Calm down!
报告情况，联系他们!
Understand the situation and communicate clearly!
所有的火力压制，你上去
Pull the chain on all the firepower you can get on that mountain!
Alert Crandall 遇到敌人
Alert Crandall! We have a hot LZ!!
Agent Serpent-Six, 这是Trojan2
Agent Serpent-Six, this is Trojan-Two.
你正在进入敌人火力 正在交火
You're coming into a hot LZ. We are taking fire.
重复 我们正在交火
Repeat. We are taking fire.
不，shit
No shit.
太高了 下去
This is Too Tall goin' down and dirty.
收到 Troyjan2,完毕
Roger that! Trojan-Two, out!
Herrick的排被切断，遭到攻击
Herrick's platoon is cut off and under attack.
Bravo 队伍守住
Bravo Company's holding.
他们正在尝试从侧面攻击我们
They're gonna try and flank us.
下去，行动
On the ground now! Move!
看他 我们必须去
- Watch him! - We gotta go.
我们出来了
We're outta here.
他们正从背面过来，走
They're coming at us from the back now! Move!
Savage.
好了 拿到了
All right, all right, I got you.
Sir?
不要让他们截取信号密码
Don't let them get the signal codes.
是,sir
Roger that, sir.
为国家而死我很自豪
I'm glad I could die for my country.
救护兵
Doc.
Bungum.
Sarge?
告诉我太太
Tell my wife...
我爱她
I love her.
这是Savage
This is Savage.
我需要火炮到这些坐标 niner-3-3-0-1
I need artillery to these coordinates: niner-3-3-0-1
Ernie,帮忙 多一些
Ernie! Ernie, help! We got more coming!
我们被切断了 重复，我们被切断了
We are cut off. Copy? We are cut off.
开火 开火
- Fire! - Fire!
开火
他们靠近了
They're getting closer!
他们靠近了 一百多人,sir
They're getting closer! A hundred more, sir!
他们在我们上面，sir 让它近点
They're right on top of us, sir! Bring it in close!
开火了，要跳下去，不能着陆了
It's a hot LZ! We'll be jumping! We will not touch down.
他们想分开我们
They're trying to break right through us!
我想要你去帮助 Alpha队伍那边，出发
I want you to reinforce Alpha Company there! Now! Move!
跟着我 Charlie,占领那个点
Follow me! Charlie Company, up on the ridge!
救护兵,受伤者在那边 靠着蚁窝过去
Doc, the wounded are over by that termite mound! Go!
sir 如果你不找一些掩护 你会被击中的
Sir, if you don't find some cover, you're gonna go down!
如果你倒下了，我们全都完了 快点
If you go down, we all go down! Come on!
Cobain!
我需要 M-60 这里
I want the M-60 right here!
通讯兵
Radio!
sir,爱德华上尉 在山梁上,sir
Sir, it's Captain Edwards on the ridge, sir!
- 鲍伯 - 上校 ,这些家伙是普通兵
- Bob! - Colonel, these guys are regulars!
全副武装的 AK-47，手榴弹
Heavily armed! AK-47s and pouches of grenades!
重机枪 火箭筒
Heavy machine guns and shoulder-fired rockets!
Nadal上尉
Captain Nadal!
河床是重要的 重要的
That creek bed is vital. Vital!
他们正朝你冲过来 不要让他们攻击侧面
They'll be coming right at you! Do not let them flank!
重复,不要让他们攻击侧面
I repeat, do not let them flank!
守住河床
Secure the creek bed!
汤姆,你继续保护那些Medevac男孩
Tom, I want you to keep trying to raise those Medevac boys.
我没事
I'm all right.
查理,这里
Charlie, come here.
叫来所有的空中支援 攻下那座山! 现在
Get me all the air support you can get me on that mountain! Now!
请求立即空中支援
Requesting immediate close air support!
我需要你烧光他们
I need you to burn 'em out...
在Alpha山顶 转到Alpha Bravo
on hilltop Alpha, shift to Alpha Bravo!
坐标: Golf-4-5-0-9
Coordinates: Golf-4-5-0-9!
－高些 - 改到Bravo山顶
- Get me something higher up! - Shifting to hilltop Bravo!
Golf-4-5-7-2!
重复,4-5-7-2
I say again, 4-5-7-2!
第7骑兵师的Medevac指挥 你在那边吗
Medevac Command of the 7th Cavalry, are you inbound?
下面看起来很热
Looks pretty hot down there.
是的，但是你可以做到 看着我们，跟下来
Yeah. You can make it, though. Watch our approach, follow us in.
知道了 我们跟着你
Copy that, 7th Cav. We will follow your approach.
我要你去那里 加强Charlie分队
I want you to get over there and reinforce Charlie Company there!
Medevac,放弃! 这是热的LZ
Medevac, abort! Abort! This is a hot LZ!
你看见那? 我的弟兄在外面，留下受伤者
You see that? My Medevac guys are buggin' out and leaving the wounded!
我们正在下来
We're going down!
- Snake,出去 - 把伤员带过来
- Snake, get out of here! - Bring me the wounded!
伤员，带受伤者
Wounded! Get the wounded!
快点
Come on! Come on!
好,这里
Okay, here!
他们仍在尝试攻击我们侧面 在外面沿线伸展
They're still trying to flank us! Stretch out along the line!
通讯兵
Radio!
Troyjan6 我们遇到猛烈攻击 不行了
Trojan-Six! We are in heavy contact! In danger of being overrun!
如果他们进入 LZ 我们马上到，你能坚持吗
If they get into that LZ, we've all had it. Can you hold?
我们快不行了,sir 但是我们会守住
We're spread thin, sir, but we'll give 'em hell!
Crandall,这是Troyjan6 这里太激烈了
Crandall, this is Trojan-Six. It's too hot down here.
- 我正在接近 LZ  - 你重复,Too tall?
- I'm closing the LZ. - You copy that, Too Tall?
重复,Snake
Copy that, Snake.
所有第7空降师: LZ 关闭X光
All 7th Cav air units: LZ X-Ray is closed.
我不喜欢它，第一次 整个营大屠杀
I don't like it. First time out, a whole battalion massacred?
你认为这是大屠杀
You think this is a massacre?
战斗失利是个坏星期 损失上校是大屠杀
Losing draftees is a bad week. Losing a colonel is a massacre.
摩尔仍在守住
Moore is still fighting.
他在和数不清的敌人对抗
He's under strength against more men than he can count.
- 他整个的排死了 - 他们不会的
- He's got a whole platoon lost. - They're not lost.
他们想切断，包围
They're only cut off and surrounded.
然后他们完了
Then they're lost.
长官 sir
- Sergeant Major! - Sir!
我们需要从那里紧急撤离
We need to carve out an emergency LZ right over there.
sir 放倒树
- Sir! - Blow the trees down!
手雷
Fire in the hole!
上校,这是Snakeshit，还有Too tall
Colonel, this is Snakeshit and Too Tall.
我们来了，带了两箱弹药
We're comin' in with two loads of ammo.
Crandall,我们开了新的LZ
Crandall, we've blown a new LZ.
当你来的时候，从东部过来，完毕
When you come in, come in from the east. Out.
上校,队总部 他们想要你去
Colonel, it's Brigade Headquarters. They want you out.
- 我们不能出去,该死 - 不是我们，只有你
- Well, we can't get out, damn it! - Not all of us. Just you.
西贡想要和你说
Saigon wants to debrief you.
- 他们什么都不懂 - 再一次说
- That doesn't make any sense. - Say again.
你重复那个命令好吗
Will you repeat that order?
Too tall,跟着上校 到新的LZ
Too Tall, follow the colonel to the new LZ.
我看见他了,Snake
I see him, Snake.
他在这里，走
He's right here! Let's go! Move!
行动
Let's move! Move!
Oh, shit.
- 快，我帮你 - 我们继续前进
- Come on! We'll give you a hand! - We're moving on board!
好的,拿上弹药带上伤员
All right, get that ammo off and get the wounded on!
带来了
Bring 'em on! Get 'em on, boys!
我们拿不动了
No, we're overloaded!
留下他 我要出去，是雷
- Leave him! - I'll get out! It's Ray!
他比我伤得更厉害
He's hurt worse than me!
你挂在上面 我看着你,雷
You hang on! I'll see you back there, Ray!
你，我和奥略立特，我们互相看着
You, me and Ouellette are all we have in reserve.
好了，松一点了
Yeah, but it's slacking up a little.
不，他们正在重新编组 准备另外攻击
No, they're just regrouping for another assault.
分配弹药
Distribute that ammo.
奥略立特, 告诉柯兰多他还能来一次。
Ouellette, tell Crandall he's got time to get one more flight in here.
是,sir
Yes, sir.
医生, 你把这些水给受伤者
Doc, you give this water to the wounded.
水快完了，糟糕
Running out of water. Must be terrible for 'em.
那些家伙被切断
Those guys are cut off out there.
节省弹药,Sarge
Running low on ammo, Sarge!
瞄准目标，一枪杀一个
Pick your target. One shot, one kill.
知道了,Sarge 我们如何做,医生
- Roger that, Sarge. - How we doin', Doc?
奥利,我们没水了
Ernie, we're out of water.
那是最后的了
That's the last of it.
我的脸着火了，帮忙
My face is on fire! Help!
福斯特，稳住 稳住
Foster, hold still! Hold still!
我来割开你的脸 稳住
I'll cut your face! Hold still!
医生,是Foster
Doc, Doc, it's Foster!
好的
Okay.
谁还有绷带?
Does anybody have any more bandages?
Ernie,你也中弹了?
Ernie, you hit too? You hit?
没有,我很好
No, no, I'm okay.
大家正在赶过来是吗
Our guys are gonna come for us, aren't they?
是的
Yeah.
何时?
When?
插入他的伤口
Plug his wound.
那是主要的 LZ, 但是它关闭了
That's the main LZ, but it's closed.
都下去
Go! Move!
Parker  上那里去 这是too tall。完毕
Go, Parker! Get up in there! This is too Tall. I'm clear...
Crandall完毕
Crandall's clear...
上校
Colonel!
去那边帮他们 那个山梁上
Go over and reinforce that company! On that ridge there! Look!
是，sir 好! 低下头
Yes, sir! Okay! Keep your head down!
到山上!快
To the top of the ridge! Move it!
快走
Come on, let's move! Move!
跑! 快点
Run! Come on!
Nadal,我们要去救那个排
Captain Nadal, we've got to break through to that cutoff platoon!
那边有个美国排
We got an American platoon out there.
一个空降排被堵在那里!
An Air Cav platoon cut off out there!
空降兵
Air Cav!
Garry Owen!
他说,"是吗?还有我。" 我说,"知道了。
He said, "Really? Me too." I said, "I know.
你妈妈让我给你 $600."
Your mama asked me to give you $600."
祝你好运
Good luck to you.
嗨, 还装得下一个吗?
Hey, you got enough room for one more?
如果你疯了,上来吧 是的,sir
If you're crazy enough, get in. Yes, sir.
嗨,下面那些光是什么?
Hey, what are those lights down there?
敌人的军队
Enemy soldiers.
他们在点火把行军
They use candles on the trail.
他们要进入攻击位置
They're moving into position to attack.
走
Here we go!
跳下去!
Unload that shit! Let's go, let's go, let's go, let's go!
你们今天完成了一件可怕的任务，Snake
You and your boys have done a hell of a job today, Snake.
这是夜里最后一次飞行, 如果你需要,再呼叫我们
It's the last flight for the night, but you need us, you call us.
你是谁? 我是记者，sir
Who in the hell are you? I'm a reporter, sir.
哦
Yeah.
Joe Galloway, UPI 怎样了, 上校?
Joe Galloway, UPI. How's it going, Colonel?
我们从昨晚以来一直被压在这里 而且我们人太少了
We've been flat to the boards since last night, and we're outnumbered.
更多的敌人要过来了 我看见火把沿山向下过来
More enemy coming too. I saw a chain of lights coming down the mountain.
是吗? 是的,sir
Is that so? Yes, sir.
好吧，我不能保证你的安全
Well, I can't guarantee your safety.
是的,sir,我知道
Yes, sir, I know.
你从哪里来? Refugio，德克萨斯，先生
Where you from, son? Refugio, Texas, sir.
这是我今天听到的第一件好事
Well, that's the first thing I heard all day that makes any sense.
上尉,你看那些火把过来了吗?
Captain, you see those lights coming down the trails on the mountain?
开火了，sir。 把这些婊子烤干
On it right now, sir. You fry them sons of bitches.
Whiskey6,这是Troyjan3 要开火了
Whiskey-Six, this is Trojan-Three. Fire mission.
Tango Foxtrot: 4-niner-6-5-6-niner.
傍晚停止所有行动
All operations are suspended for the evening.
早上5:30开始行动
Morning operations will be scheduled for 0530 hours.
Crandall在哪里?
Where's Crandall?
Crandall? 在那边,sir
Where's Crandall? He's right there, sir.
你带他们人过去
You led my men into a hot LZ.
必须把伤员运走
Somebody had to fly out the wounded.
别和我耍花招 你再这样我要你好看
Don't you play hotshot with me. You know the rules.
你干掉我们了 再来一次啊,操死你
You suckered us in there. Do it again, I'll have you busted!
你朝我开火 却不是朝敌人?
You got the balls to face me, but not the balls to face the enemy?
让开
Get outta here. Whoa!
让我再看见,我会杀了你
I ever see you again, I'll kill you.
算了
That's right.
辛苦的一天,哼!?
Quite a day, huh?
明天将会更糟糕
Tomorrow will be worse.
他们能否撑到明天
If they make it to tomorrow.
Ernie, 太黑了 我看不见任何东西，但可以闻到
Ernie, it's pitch black. I can't see anything, but I can smell 'em.
死尸的臭味,Bungum
Dead bodies stink, Bungum.
不是来自死尸的 我能闻出他们爬过来了
No, it's not the dead ones. I can smell them crawling up on us.
我正要告诉你
I'm telling you.
照明弹,6-5-0,1-5-0
I need illumination, 6-5-0, 1-5-0.
火炮朝原定目标射击
I need artillery on previously established targets!
Alpha,Bravo和Charlie!火力掩护
Alpha, Bravo and Charlie! Fire for effect!
上啊
Fire for effect!
节省弹药 停火
Save your ammo! Cease fire!
有人受伤吗?
Is anybody hit?
上尉，如果你的人要来了，告诉我们
Captain, if you guys are coming you gotta let us know.
太黑了，我可不想射到自己人
It's pitch black out here. I don't wanna shoot any of our own guys.
Savage...
我们守不过今晚了
we can't make it tonight.
不要担心，会守住的
Don't worry. You're gonna make it.
我们会在早晨来增援
We'll come get you in the morning.
是,sir
Yes, sir.
完毕
Out.
干得好
You're doing a fine job, son.
别担心，我们今天比他们做得好多了
Don't worry. We gave them more than they gave us today.
你的人怎么样了? 很好,sir
How you boys doing? Fine, sir.
那继续干 我们会没事的
You keep doing what you're doing, we'll be fine.
你们今天干得漂亮，中尉
Your men have done a hell of a job today, Lieutenant Geoghegan.
他们过不来,sir 你可以相信我
They won't get through us, sir. You can count on it.
知道了,杰克
I know that, Jack.
继续
Keep it up, son.
后方总部的，sir
It's Rear Headquarters, sir.
你那里好吗,上校?
How is it out there, Colonel?
我们被包围了，但是我们在坚持，sir
We're surrounded, but we're holding on, sir.
sir, 我需要知道我们的伤亡数字
Sir, I need a confirmed count of our dead and wounded.
我还不知道我的人在哪里
I got to know where all my boys are.
你会知道的,Hal
You'll get it, Hal.
他们来了
Here they come.
爱德华
Captain Edwards.
周围投照明弹
We need illumination on the perimeter.
Whiskey5 这是Hot Wire-Six-Alpha
Whiskey-Five, this is Hot Wire-Six-Alpha.
我们现在需要照明
We need illumination now.
凯西?
Kathy?
电报
A telegram.
有份电报
A cab delivers a telegram.
"军队秘书组...
"The Secretary of the Army...
...抱歉..."
regrets..."
摩尔太太?
Mrs. Moore?
摩尔上校的太太?
Colonel Moore's wife?
是的
Yes.
我需要帮忙找个住址
I need help finding an address.
我以为... 你这混蛋!
I'm looking for... You jackass!
你知道这是什么吗? 你知道你刚才在做什么吗?
Do you know what this is? Do you know what you just did to me?
我也不想这样，夫人
I don't like this job, ma'am.
我试着做这个
I'm just trying to do it.
等一下
Wait.
我来送给她
I'll take it to her.
告诉他们, 如果还有其他的，都交给我
And tell the cab company, if there are any others, just bring them to me.
Julie.
我来看看凯萨琳
I just went by to see Catherine.
大家都知道了
Everybody knows.
没有牧师或顾问? 送信的?
No chaplains or counselors? Cab drivers?
军方没准备好
The Army wasn't ready.
我和你一起去
I'll go with you.
谢谢 这是给谁的?
Thanks. Who's it for?
她会恨我吧
I thought she would hate me.
不是你丈夫开始战争
Your husband didn't start the war.
他们都知道会这样的,我们也是
They all knew this could happen, and so did we.
我会参加的
I'll take care of this.
我和你一起去
I'll go with you.
我们一个个来
We'll do one at a time. Okay?
先不看
We won't look.
好的
Okay.
朱莉
Julie...
明天会有更多电报吗?
do you think there'll be more telegrams tomorrow?
如果有,来叫上我
If there are, come and get me.
因父之名 the Son and the Holy Ghost,阿门
In the name of the Father, the Son and the Holy Ghost, amen.
Out of the depths I cry unto Thee, O Lord.
主, 听我的祈祷
Lord, hear my voice.
听我虔诚的祈求吧
Let Thine ears be attentive to the voice of my supplications.
主啊 接受我们的崇敬
Thou, O Lord, shall mark our inequities.
主, 不要放弃他们
Lord, who can abide them?
用你的怜悯
With Thee there is mercy.
守护他们永生, 主啊
Grant them eternal rest, O Lord...
愿永生之光照耀他们
and may perpetual light shine upon them.
愿你保佑他们安息
And through the mercy of God, may they rest in peace. Amen.
因主之名, the Son and the Holy Ghost
In the name of the Father, the Son and the Holy Ghost.
你想死吗，Galloway?
Do you got a death wish, Galloway?
不,sir
No, sir.
那你为什么来这里?
Well, then why are you here?
因为我知道这些死者在这里，sir。
'Cause I knew these dead boys would be here, sir.
为什么你不是军人?
Why aren't you a soldier?
你够胆量
You got the guts for it.
我爸爸是个军人
My daddy was a soldier.
我爷爷,我的两个曾爷爷都是军人
My granddaddy, two of my great-granddaddies was soldiers.
这就是原因
Hell, that's how I came to be.
他们每人在内战中失去了一条腿
Each of them lost a leg in the Civil War.
我曾爷爷Galloway,他失去了左腿
My Great-granddaddy Galloway, he lost his left...
我曾爷爷Reid失去了右腿
and my Great-granddaddy Reid lost his right.
他们在Galveston同一间鞋店中见面
They met in a shoe store in Galveston.
在那之後每年,相同的日期 相同的商店,他们将会聚在一起
Every year after that, same date, same store, they'd get together...
挑出一双适合他们的新鞋
and pick out a new pair of shoes for the two of them.
你开什么玩笑 不,sir
You are shittin' me. No, sir.
我发誓
I swear to God.
一个有了女儿 一个有了儿子...我的祖父们
Anyway, one had a daughter, one had a son... my grandparents.
奇怪的是他们都有相同的鞋码
What do you suppose the odds of them having the same shoe size was?
我不知道,上校 应该是,我猜
I don't know, Colonel. It was meant to be, I guess.
是的
Yeah.
可能
Meant to be.
sir, Galloways参加过这个国家的每一次战争
Sir, Galloways have been in every war this country's ever fought.
但这一次,我想我不可能结束战争
But when it came to this one, I didn't think I could stop the war.
大概是 我也想试着弄清楚点
I just thought maybe I might try and understand one.
也许可以把他们带回去 明白
Maybe help folks back home understand.
我想可以我用照相机会更好
I just figure I could do that better...
比让我来开枪
shooting a camera than I could shooting a rifle.
嗯
Well...
我希望你能做到
I sure hope you make it through this one.
你也是,上校
You too, Colonel.
右边20
Right 20!
炸死他们
Put it right on 'em!
上校,sir
Colonel, sir.
Captain Nadal. Sir.
那是什么,sir?
What is it, sir?
没什么
Nothing's wrong, except there's nothing wrong.
你最好回到白蚁土墩，继续
Best get back to the termite mound. You'll be fine. Go on.
是,sir 快点
Roger that, sir. Come on!
好的,告诉他们
All right, pass the word on.
每人对可疑之物开三枪
Every man fire three rounds at anything that looks suspicious.
听我的命令
On my signal.
他们要从四周围上来了
They're gonna hit us like this along the whole perimeter.
回白蚁土墩
We gotta get back to that termite mound.
最好呆在这里,sir
Better hang here, sir!
狗屁
Shit.
叫医生
We need a medic!
Sir! Sir!
爱德华,Charlie分队 在山梁上
Captain Edwards, Charlie Company, on the ridge.
鲍伯
Bob.
他们进入火炮射程了
They're inside the artillery!
我要
I need...
我要颗手榴弹
I need a grenade!
去,威历 走
Go, Willie! Come on, let's go!
Godboldt 趴下
Godboldt down!
我去
I'll get him!
威历
Willie!
帮他们
Get those guys help!
Dillon,让Bravo带一个排穿过LZ
Captain Dillon, get Bravo Company to send a platoon across the LZ...
去支援Charlie他们
and support Charlie Company.
Bravo6,这是Troyjan3
Bravo-Six, this is Trojan-Three.
叫Charlie他们找好掩护
And tell Charlie Company to get real small in their holes.
我要开炮了
I'm gonna drop some artillery right on top of'em!
Charlie,躲开
Charlie Company, get small.
要朝你那边开炮了
We got AT coming right on top of your position.
命中
We're being overrun!
Nah,我们要赢了
Nah, boys! We're gonna win this fight.
是的,sir,他们也增援了一个主力VC营
Yes, sir, they brought a main force of VC battalion against us too.
上校,请求增援
Colonel, I request you dispatch another company of reinforcements...
尽快赶到
for movement as soon as it can be accomplished without undue risk.
好的 很糟糕,Hal?
Done. How bad is it, Hal?
那边很不错,sir
It's getting pretty sporty down here, sir.
别挡路!
Get out of the way!
医生!过来
Medic! Get a medic over here!
你叫什么? Jimmy Nakayama
What's your name, soldier? Jimmy Nakayama.
我今天做爸爸了
I got a baby being born today.
哦! 恭喜 谢谢
Oh, wow! Congratulations! Thanks!
医生
Medic!
拍不了了 躺下
Can't take no pictures lying down there, sonny.
下面那边
Down, right there.
我不是个大兵，sir
I'm a noncombatant, sir.
今天就是了
Ain't no such thing today, boy.
狗屁
Shit.
那些人干嘛不开火?
Why aren't those mortars firing?
出什么问题了?
What's the problem here?
炮管太热,sir
These tubes are red hot, sir.
恐怕要爆了，会把我们都炸上天去的
I'm afraid we're gonna cook a round off and blow us all up.
我们没有冷却水了
We can't cool 'em off 'cause we're all out of water.
快点 你们还等什么?
Come on! What are you waiting for?
吉米,过来
Jimmy, come on.
去
Go, go, go.
是,多一些
Yeah, one more.
先生们...
Gentlemen...
准备自卫了
prepare to defend yourselves.
手雷
Grenade!
不行，让开
Negative! Negative! Stand by!
飞行员看不见敌人 他们也认不出自己人
My pilots do not see the enemy. They cannot pick out our friendlies.
Bravo6,重复
Bravo-Six, say again.
让大家放烟幕
You gotta tell your company commander to pop smoke now.
他们要作标记 我们没有标线
They need to mark the lines now! We have no lines!
敌人和自己人都在一起
We have enemies and friendlies mixed in all over the place.
sir,周围挡不住了
Sir, our perimeter is collapsing.
A和B队不行了
Alpha Company and Bravo Company cannot hold.
C队也快撑不住
Charlie Company is being overrun.
呼叫!呼叫
Net call! Net call!
保持联络!
Keep this net clear!
Hastings!
Broken arrow!
重复 Broken arrow
I say again! Broken arrow!
We have broken arrow! We have broken arrow!
确定。Broken arrow
Confirm. Broken arrow.
Broken arrow确认
Broken arrow confirmed.
Broken arrow?
意思是美国人被打败了
That means that an American unit has been overrun.
请求支援的信号
It calls in every combat aircraft for support.
不要躲了
My God, there's no hiding it now.
C队,报告 信号断了
Charlie Company, report! Signal is out!
B队,报告
Bravo Company, report!
收到 飞机快到了,上校
Roger that! Planes are on their way, Colonel!
Sir!
收到
Roger that!
飞机以每 1,000 尺...
We have planes at every 1,000 feet...
从 7,000 到 35,000 我们看到了,sir
from 7,000 to 35,000... we'll get 'em, sir!
北边 在我们的位置上1-5-0
Advancing north on our position at 1-5-0.
Nine-six-two-five-zero-seven--
他们靠近了315度
They're getting closer in on 3-1-5 degrees!
0-5-0 重复,0-5-0
That's 0-5-0! Repeat, 0-5-0!
妈的
Goddamn it.
暴露目标了,我们北边
Company sighted out in the open, advancing north on our position.
他们在315 度偏1-5-0
They're advancing on 3-1-5 degrees at 1-5-0.
近点在315度偏0-5-0
Bring it closer in on 3-1-5 degrees at 0-5-0...
Charlie,让他们滚
Charlie, call that son of a bitch off!
呼叫中止
Call an abort now!
出来
Pull up!
蹲下
Get down!
Charlie,听我说 你保证我们活下来
Charlie, listen to me. You're keeping us alive now.
你忘了，怎么让他们过来了
You forget about that one and you keep 'em coming in.
做得好
You're doing well, son.
七-二
Seven-oh-two...
对着那些树打
Attack against the tree line.
医生
Medic! Medic!
吉米 你认识这家伙?
Oh, God! Jimmy. You know this guy?
你认识他?和他说话
You know him? Talk to him. Just talk to him!
吉米,你能听到我吗?
Jimmy, do you hear me?
是乔，Joe Galloway
It's Joe. It's Joe Galloway.
医生给你吗啡 要带你离开
Doc's giving you morphine. We're gonna get you out of here.
把他带到着陆点，抓住他
We gotta get him to the landing zone. Grab his legs!
带他离开
You gotta get him out of here. Hey! Hey!
我不能帮你了 你要自己做
I can't help you! You gotta do it by yourself!
把他带到直升机 是,sir
Get him on that chopper, okay? Yes, sir.
告诉我妻子，我爱她
Tell my wife I love her...
还有我的孩子
and my baby!
你告诉他们
You tell'em!
Captain Nadal. Sir...
现在他们不行了，我们歇歇
Now that we put 'em back on their heels, we got us a lull.
我想要你进攻
I want you to attack.
你去那里援救被切断的排
I want you to go over there and rescue that cut off platoon.
是,sir 一班,出发
Yes, sir! First Squad, move out!
大家快走
Come on, guys. Move it!
另外五十
Add fifty.
继续向前移动火炮
Keep moving the artillery forward!
让火炮向前走
Keep walking the artillery forward!
推进
Spread it out!
动起来
Move it!
向前走
Move it! Keep moving forward!
Savage，你们还在这里?
Sergeant Savage, you guys still here?
有 40 KIA,2 MIA
We have 40 KIA, we have two MIA.
最近的数字，完毕
These are the latest numbers. Over.
美好的一天，Savage
That's a nice day, Sergeant Savage.
死了40，两个失踪，sir
Forty dead, two unaccounted for, sir.
知道了
Right.
好了，冲啊，带上他们
All right, boys, let's get 'em up and get 'em out.
带他们离开这里上直升机
Let's get 'em out of here and get 'em on the chopper!
大部分人都装上飞机了
Since most of the men being loaded on the chopper...
C队的
are from Charlie Company...
你去取代他们
I want you to take their place.
我带路。跟着我 是,sir!走
I'll show you where. Follow me. Yes, sir! Let's go!
上尉,让你的人准备开火
Captain, have your men dig some firing steps.
尸体上放些泥压住味道
Throw some dirt on those bodies, keep the smell down.
是，长官
Roger, Sergeant Major.
这次损失惨重
Kind of makes you wish you'd signed up for submarines, don't it?
参谋部要你跟凌晨第一架飞机回去
Brigade headquarters wants you out on the first chopper at dawn.
笨蛋，我怎么能离开战场
What idiot would keep ordering that in the middle of a goddamn battle?
Westmoreland将军需要听取报告 给我话筒
Gen. Westmoreland wants a briefing. Give me the horn.
我正在战斗
I am in a fight...
拒绝执行回西贡的命令
and I object to this order to return to Saigon.
现在，我不会丢下我的人
Now, I will not leave my men.
明白吗? 完毕
Is that clear? Out.
两个人不见了
There's two of my men unaccounted for out there...
在战斗最激烈的那边
and it's where the worst of the fighting was...
他们会在哪里
so they'll be out there someplace.
我们去找他们 我和你一起去,sir
Let's go out and get 'em. I'm with you, sir.
好吧
All right.
走
Let's go.
他们...
They...
带来另一个
brought another...
Julie Julie,你的
Oh, God, Julie. Julie, it's yours.
他为了我的承诺而死
He died keeping my promise.
sir，他们命令我们都出去
Sir, they're ordering us all out.
全部
All of us.
他们将要火力支援
They're gonna march reinforcements in.
他们不清楚这里
They don't understand a damn thing, do they?
不能出去
Can't get out.
他正在洞里等着我们 想要我们出去
He's waiting up there in a cave, and that's what he wants.
他一见到有人跳下飞机
The minute he sees live soldiers hopping on a helicopter...
就会扑上来，那他得逞了
he'll be all over us and then he'll get what he wants.
接着就是大屠杀
He'll get his massacre.
请求许可再部署
Requesting permission to rejoin the lines, sir.
同意
All right, son.
Garry Owen, sir.
Custer在想什么
I wonder what was going through Custer's mind when he realized...
他把他的人带进了屠杀
he'd led his men into a slaughter.
sir, Custer是只猫
Sir, Custer was a pussy.
你不是
You ain't.
见鬼
Goddamn.
去死
Hell.
他们正在准备最后的进攻
Right now they're planning their final attack...
这会让我们没命
the one that will finish us off.
他们会在晚上一点点地吞噬我们
They'll nibble at us all night, then...
凌晨他们将竭尽全力冲上来
come dawn they'll hit us with everything they got.
如果我是他，我就这么做
That's what I'd do if I was him.
长官,发下最后的弹药
Sergeant Major, hand out the last of the ammunition.
是,sir
Yes, sir.
上刺刀
Fix bayonets.
你在想Custer感觉如何,先生
You were wondering how Custer felt, sir.
你应该去问他
You ought to ask him.
Sergeant Savage!
检查敌人的文件
Checking the dead enemies for documents...
我在那个想刺死你的家伙身上发现这东西
and I found this on the guy that tried to bayonet you.
翻译一些
Translated some of it, mostly personal.
希望你愿意看一眼
Thought you might wanna have a look at it.
那是什么? 美国的火炮
What was that? It's American artillery.
自己人
Friendly fire.
多少伤亡?
How many casualties?
这里怎么了,乔?
What the hell happened here, Joe?
嗨，乔
Hey, Joe.
摩尔上校
Colonel Moore!
上校
Colonel! Colonel Moore!
你胜利的关键是什么? 先生, 告诉我们你感觉如何
What is the key to your victory? Sir, tell us how you feel.
你感觉美国将会被迫
Do you feel the States will be forced...
更加残酷地对待北越人吗？
to take the North Vietnamese more seriously?
你对那些死去的手下怎么看,sir?
How do you feel about the loss of your men, sir?
你通知他们家庭了吗
Have you notified the families, sir?
很高兴你做到了
I'm glad you made it, son.
谢谢你,sir 你也是
Thank you, sir. You too.
我不会原谅自己
I'll never forgive myself.
为什么,sir
For what, sir?
我的部下...
That my men...
他们死了而我却活着
That my men died and I didn't.
sir, 我不
Sir, I don't...
我不知道该如何讲这个故事
I don't know how to tell this story.
该你了,乔
Well, you got to, Joe.
你告诉美国人这些人在这里所做的
You tell the American people what these men did here.
告诉他们我的骑兵们如何战死
You tell 'em how my troopers died.
是,sir
Yes, sir.
谢谢
Thank you.
我们所有人，活着的或是死去的 都离开战场了，sir
All of our men, living and dead, are off the field, sir.
很好
Well done, Sergeant Major.
在西贡,Hal Moore的长官祝贺他
In Saigon, Hal Moore's superiors congratulated him...
他们打死了超过 1,800个敌人
for killing over 1,800 enemy soldiers.
然后命令他带领第7骑兵师
Then ordered him to lead the men of the 7th Cavalry...
回到死亡山谷中
back into the Valley of Death.
他带领他们
He led them...
和他们共同奋战
and fought beside them...
又坚持了235天
for 235 more days.
孩子们,睡觉去了 谁在敲门？
Kids, go to bed. Isn't there someone at the door?
睡觉去
Go to bed!
孩子,爸爸回家了 爸爸!
Children, your daddy's home! Daddy!
家人在等着我们回去
Some had families waiting.
还有很多人受伤了
For others, their only family would be the men they bled beside.
没有乐团, 没有彩旗
There were no bands, no flags...
没有荣誉欢迎他们回家
no honor guards to welcome them home.
国家命令他们去作战
They went to war because their country ordered them to.
但最后他们不是为国家或旗帜而战
But in the end they fought not for their country or their flag.
他们为了彼此而战
They fought for each other...
亲爱的芭芭拉...
Dear Barbara...
杰克死了我也很伤心
I have no words to express to you my sadness of the loss of Jack.
没有他世界变得无趣
The world is a lesser place without him.
但我知道他正陪伴着上帝和天使
But I know he is with God and the angels.
因为他的存在天堂也随之美好
And even heaven is improved by his presence there.
你也是这么想的吧
I know you, too, are sure of this...
尽管知道这些不能弥补他的离去
and yet this knowledge can't diminish his loss...
减少你的悲伤
and your grief.
Hal Moore敬上
With abiding respect and affection, Hal Moore.
我们曾看到过战争
We who have seen war...
从不忘怀
will never stop seeing it.
在静静的夜晚 我们总会听到尖叫声
In the silence of the night, we will always hear the screams.
这就是我们的故事
So this is our story...
因为我们曾是战士
for we were soldiers once...
而且年轻
and young.